Elias Newman
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Elias Newman papers
1922-1981
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Newman, Elias
1.1 linear feet
The papers of New York painter, writer, and educator Elias Newman measure 1.1 linear feet and date from 1922 to 1981. Newman's participation in exhibitions and various art related organizations, notably Artists Equity Association, is documented through biographical material, correspondence, notes, writings, organizational records, printed material, and photographs.
Provenance
The collection was donated in 1977 and 1981 by Elias Newman.
Alternative Forms Available
The collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reels 4860-4861 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Elias Newman (1903-1999) was a painter, writer, lecturer, and teacher in New York, N.Y. Born in Stashow, Poland in 1903, Newman arrived in the United States in 1913, and became a naturalized citizen in 1928. He studied at the National Academy of Design from 1919-1920, and at the Educational Alliance Art School from 1920-1925. He also studied at the Academie Chaumiere in Paris. After 1925, Newman participated in many exhibitions, acted as art director of the Palestine Pavilion at the New York World's Fair in 1939, organized the Palestine Artists and Sculptors Association, and was director of the National Society of Painters in Casein in 1963 and 1967-1971. From 1970-1975, Newman served as president of the Artists Equity Association, the organization which played the most significant role in his career.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of New York painter, writer, and educator Elias Newman measure 1.1 linear feet and date from 1922 to 1981. Newman's participation in exhibitions and various art related organizations, notably Artists Equity Association, is documented through biographical material, correspondence, notes, writings, organizational records, printed material, and photographs.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 6 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1935-1975 (Box 1; 1 folder)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1927-1980 (Box 1; 8 folders)
Series 3: Writings, circa 1939-1976 (Box 1; 4 folders)
Series 4: Artists Equity Association Records, circa 1950-1979 (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1922-1981 (Box 1, OV 2; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 6: Photographs, 1923-1975 (Box 1; 9 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Artists Equity Association
Subjects-Topical:
Art, Jewish; Authors--New York (State)--New York; Educators--New York (State)--New York; Jewish artists; Painting, Modern--20th century--New York (State)--New York; Painters--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Photographs; Notes
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1935-1975, Series 1:; (Box 1; 1 folder)
  Biographical material includes a membership card for the Palestine Artists and Sculptors Association, 1935, a biographical account, 1975, a resume, and list of one-man shows, 1956.
  - Biographical Material, 1935-1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1927-1980, Series 2:; (Box 1; 8 folders)
  Correspondence reflects Newman's participation in exhibitions and various organizations, and includes letters concerning his requests for government grants.
  Correspondence is arranged chronologically.
  - Correspondence, undated, 1927-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1957 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1971-1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Writings, circa 1939-1976, Series 3:; (Box 1; 4 folders)
  The writings series consists notes; typescripts of reviews from 1949-1962; 9 typescripts for articles including America-Israel: New Worlds in the Making, An Executive Committee or a National Organization?, Jews in Art, Professionalism in the Fine Arts; a typescript and printed copy of Newman's book Art in Palestine, 1939; a eulogy for Nathaniel Dirk; a copy of a speech delivered at the Educational Alliance Art School, 1974; and an essay Pictures Speak Louder than Words by Henry Montor, 1939.
  - Notes, 1962-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Writings by Elias Newman, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Writings by Elias Newman, 1948-1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Writings by Others, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Artists Equity Association Records, circa 1950-1979, Series 4:; (Box 1; 0.3 linear feet)
  Material relating to the Artists Equity Association contains a constitution; correspondence with members and congressmen, primarily concerning the tax reform bill; budget projections for 1956-1959; notes concerning agenda and procedures; 4 typescripts of speeches for occasions honoring Lloyd Goodrich, Chaim Gross, Roy Neuberger, and congressman Ogden R. Reid; clippings; AEA exhibition announcements; a membership list; a calendar of events; and photographs of AEA events attended by Hy Cohen, Nathaniel Dirk, Ernest Fiene, Helen Gerardia, Leah Gold, Maxwell Gordon, Leon Kroll, Sidney Laufman, Ralph Mayer, Daniel Millsaps, Philip Reisman, Stuyvesant Van Veen, Hudson Walker, and Sol Wilson.
  - Constitution, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, undated, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1958-1959 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1961-1969 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1971, (6 folders) (Box 1, Folder 20-25)
  - Correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Financial Material, 1956-1959 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Notes, 1957-1971 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Writings, 1962-1976 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Clippings, 1971-1978 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1952-1964 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Miscellaneous Printed Material, 1950-1962 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Photographs of events, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Printed Material, 1922-1981, Series 5:; (Box 1, OV 2; 0.4 linear feet)
  Printed material includes clippings, exhibition announcements and catalogs, three prospectuses, and brochures advertising Newman's classes and abilities as a lecturer. Also found are three exhibition posters, including two from shows in Israel.
  - Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Clippings, 1922-1929 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Clippings, 1930-1935 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Clippings, 1936-1939 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Clippings, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Clippings, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Clippings, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Clippings, 1970-1980 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1927-1929 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1934-1938 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1940-1947 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1955-1959 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1960-1963 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1964-1969 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1970-1975 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Exhibition Announcements and Catalogs, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Prospectives, 1960-1969 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Book, Art in Palestine by Elias Newman [typescript], 1939 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Book, Art in Palestine by Elias Newman, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Brochures about Newman, undated, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Miscellaneous Brochures, 1940-1959 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Reproductions of works of art, undated (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Posters, 1930, 1962, 1970 (Box OV 2)
- Photographs, 1923-1975, Series 6:; (Box 1; 9 folders)
  Found here are 41 photographs of Newman, including one with classmates Peter Blume and Moses Soyer, 1923, one of Newman at the 1939 World's Fair, and one with poet Hy Korin; 17 photographs of events, showing Newman's colleagues Samuel Adler, Henry Botkin, Emma Ehrenreich, Ernest Fiene, Maxwell Gordon, Chaim Gross, Lena Gurr, Joseph Hirsch, Edward Hopper, Howard Kuh, Naomi Lorne, Bernard Simon, and Anthony Toney; and 15 photographs of works by Newman.
  - Photographs of Elias Newman, 1923-1939 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Photographs of Elias Newman, 1940-1949 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Photographs of Elias Newman, 1950-1959 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Photographs of Elias Newman, 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Newman teaching art classes, 1942, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Miscellaneous events, 1948-1975 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Works of art, undated (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Works of art, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Works by others, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 70)